Guide to John W. Fulton papers 1897-1966
Montana Historical Society
John W. Fulton papers
1897-1966
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 410
Fulton, John W.
1.5 linear foot of shelf space
John W. Fulton's papers (1897-1966) include a letterpress book of outgoing correspondence; a cash journal and miscellaneous invoices for the Plymouth Gold Mining Company; diaries primarily of business activities; stock certificates for the Montana Gold Mines Syndicate and the Montana Leasing and Mining Company. There are 2 subgroups for two of companies: the Big Ox Mining Company, and the Northern Angora Goat Company which both include, but are not limited to correspondence and financial records
Biographical Note
John Wilson Fulton was born in Massachusetts on October 26, 1872, the son of Charles J. and Mary Anne (Wilson) Fulton. About 1892 he moved to Helena, Montana, with his father, where they invested in mining properties. Their investments included the Big Ox Mining Company, the Plymouth Gold Mining Company at Gould, and other mines. The Big Ox Mining Company firm was incorporated on October 16, 1896 by John, Charles, and M.A.H. Fulton. They purchased the mining properties of the Big ox Mining and Reduction Company near Marysville, Montana. The company operated the Big Ox Mine and the Golconda Mine until about 1916, when the corporate charter expired. On May 17, 1920, John and Charles re-incorporated under the same name. The company went bankrupt and in 1926 the Fultons organized Montana Mines (an Express Trust) to buy the properties at sheriff's sales. They continued to operate the properties until the mid 1930s. The Northern Angora Goat Company was formed as the Northern Angora Goat & Live Stock Co. in 1900. The company's home office was the Pittsburgh Block in Helena, Montana, with the Mohair Sales Depot and Eastern Office in Boston, Massachusetts. The original officers included Charles W. Hoffman of Bozeman as president, W.C. Bailey as vice-president, George F. Thompson of Washington, D.C., as treasurer, Herbert Hammond of Chicago, Illinois, as secretary, and John Wilson Fulton of Helena, as manager. By 1904 Charles J. Fulton, took over the position as manager. He held this position until his death in February 1928. John continued to manage the company after his father's death. The firm advertised itself as the "largest breeders of long mohair Angoras in America," and promoted the goats as a new farm industry. C.J. John Wilson Fulton worked for the company from its office in the Pittsburg Block until his death on April 17, 1966. He was preceded in by his wife, Antoinette (maiden name Rathbone) Fulton, whom he married on June 29, 1911 and who passed away on December 31, 1942.
Content Description
Papers. 1897-1966, 1.5 linear foot. The collection consists of subgroups which hold general correspondence, financial records, legal documents, and organizational records of John W. Fulton and his two companies. Fulton's personal papers consist of a letterpress book of outgoing correspondence (1898-1899); a cash journal and miscellaneous invoices for the Plymouth Gold Mining Company (1897-1903) [Volume located in Oversize Box 1]; diaries of primarily business activities (1908-1910, 1912, 1914, 1916, 1917), and stock certificates for the Montana Gold Mines Syndicate and Montana Leasing and Mining Company. Entries in the diary and the correspondence relate primarily to the administration of Fulton's various businesses, and especially to stock transactions. There is some discussion of the results of mining work, e.g., discoveries of certain minerals, John's installation of telephones around the region, and a few personal notes. Fulton's business trips to both coasts are briefly mentioned. A few news clippings covering the life and death of John and his wife, Antoinette, and business filings with the Secretary of State are also included. Records in the Big Ox Mining Company subgroup include correspondence (1927-1934) with C.L. Hewitt and with stockholders, including a list of stockholders: and an expense journal (1905-1913) reflecting the day-to-day expenses of the mining operation, including wages [Oversize Volume located in Oversize Box 1]. Materials which were loose in the volume have been foldered. There is also a prospectus (1937) on the Big Ox properties by John W. Fulton, for the Montana Mine trust. Records in the Northern Angora Goat Company subgroup include incoming correspondence, consisting of a personal letter (1921) to Charles J. Fulton, and two letters (1937-1938) regarding John W. Fulton's appeal for funds: outgoing correspondence (1938) concerning a mohair fleece shipment; financial records (1932-1934); and miscellany, including a promotional flyer, a blank contact, etc. A receipt (1932) for labor at the Big Ox Mine is also included as well as an advertisement mailer for Long Mohair Goats [Oversized Folder].
Arranged by subgroup and series. Some material housed in oversize box and oversize folder. See inventory below for more information.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Research Center catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Fulton, John W.
Gould (Mont.)--Commerce; Marysville (Mont.)--Commerce
Northern Angora Goat Company; Plymouth Gold Mining Company; Goats-- Montana--Lewis and Clark County (Mont.); Gold mines and mining--Lewis and Clark County (Mont.)
Montana; Mines and Mineral Resources; Business, Industry, and Labor
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- John W. Fulton Personal Papers
  - Diaries
    - John W. Fulton Diaries, 1908-1917 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing
    - Letterpress book, 1898-1905 (Box-folder 2 / 1-2)
  - Financial Records
    - Cash Book of Plymouth Gold Mining Company Volume [Oversize Box], 1897-1903 (Oversizebox 1)
  - Organization Records
    - Stock certificates for the Montana Gold Mines Syndicate and Montana Leasing and Mining Company, 1900, undated (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Biographical Materials
    - News Clippings, Census and Marriage Records, Secretary of State Business Entity Filings, 1880-1966 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
- Big Ox Mining Company
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence with C.L. Hewitt and with stockholders, 1927-1934 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Financial Records
    - Receipts originally held in Expense Journal, 1905-1913 (Box-folder 2 / 6-8)
    - Expense Journal for Big Ox Mining Company Volume [Oversize Box], 1905-1913 (Oversizebox 1)
  - Legal Documents
    - Prospectus of Big Ox Mines & Mills by Montana mines (An Express Trust), 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
- Northern Angora Goat Company
  - Miscellaneous
    - Northern Angora Goat Company produce documents, undated (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - A New Farm Industry Advertisement [Oversized see Archives Map Case], undated (Oversize-folder 1)
  - General Correspondence
    - Incoming letters to Charles and John Fulton, outgoing business letter re mohair fleece shipment, 1921-1938 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Financial Records
    - Northern Angora Goat Company, 1932, 1934 (Box-folder 2 / 12)